Guide to the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project Records, 1983-1996 RL.00935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project records
1983-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project
RL.00935
24.7 Linear Feet
Access Restrictions
There are restrictions on certain sections of the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library of Duke University as a gift from the Health Project after it ceased operations in 1996.
Historical Note
The LGHP was founded in late 1982 to combat homophobia in existing health care institutions, and to provide gay men and lesbians the means to assume control over their own health care.
Collection Overview
The papers of the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project (LGHP) span the dates 1983-1996. The papers consist chiefly of correspondence, meeting minutes, newspaper clippings, newsletters, training and publicity materials, programming and services records, volunteer information, financial statements, fundraising project records, grant applications, and subject resource files. The collection also includes t-shirts, banners, and photographs. Most of the papers concern the work of the LGHP, though the Community Connections and Subject Files series both document programs and issues related to HIV/AIDS and gay/lesbian/bisexual health issues as addressed by non-profit organizations; foundations and corporations; and city, state, and federal government agencies from across North Carolina and the entire United States.
The LGHP was founded in 1982. Due to the emergence of AIDS, it quickly became the most prominent group dealing with the epidemic, and began to provide direct support services to people with AIDS. The group also provided educational programs targeting both heterosexual and gay/lesbian audiences about specific lesbian and gay health concerns and HIV/AIDS. In addition to AIDS education and services, the LGHP identified other issues, including lesbian health, as major issues of importance. However, most of the organization's fiscal and human resources were devoted to addressing HIV/AIDS. The organization grew from a small, all-volunteer group led by a Steering Committee that made all decisions by consensus, to a larger non-profit organization with staff and a Board of Directors. Through its programming, services, advocacy, and events, the group assumed a central role in fostering the gay/lesbian/bisexual community in the Triangle and in the state more generally, until its demise in early 1996.
Arrangement note
PROCESSING NOTE: Steering Committee/Board of Directors' meeting minutes, committee reports, financial statements, grant reports and other papers were sometimes stapled together and sometimes kept separate before coming to the Special Collections Library. Researchers unable to find financial records, committee or project updates, newspaper clippings, or other papers for a given date are advised to check the Steering Committee/Board of Directors minutes for that date.
The subject files maintained by the LGHP addressed a broad range of issues facing lesbian, gay, and bisexual people. For the purposes of this collection, Special Collections Library has only kept those materials related to health issues or to other issues specifically identified by the LGHP as central to its work, and deaccessioned other general materials likely to be found in other collections, at Duke University or elsewhere.
Much of the materials documenting lesbian health issues and programming as of the 1996 transfer of the collection to the Library were kept by the Lesbian Health Center, which the LGHP recognized as its successor at the time of its closing.
Durham (N.C.); Gays -- North Carolina -- Durham; Gays -- Substance abuse; Activists -- North Carolina; AIDS (Disease) -- Organizations; Sexually transmitted diseases; Gays -- Medical care; Breast -- Cancer -- Lesbians; Gays -- Mental health; Gays -- Health and hygiene; North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project
- ADMINISTRATIVE FILES SERIES
  Scope and Contents note
  The Administrative Files Series, 1983-1996,series includes annual reports, meeting minutes, Steering Committee and Board membership records, bylaws, Executive Director's reports, long-range planning materials, pamphlets, general and historical information, correspondence, staff records, and other non-financial business records of the LGHP. The Steering Committee and Board of Directors packets include the minutes of meetings of the Steering Committee, the Board, and of various committees assigned to specific projects. They also include agendas, correspondence, financial statements, budget reports, project proposals, progress reports, and final evaluations. Arranged alphabetically. Certain parts of the staff records have been closed until January 1, 2027 due to the sensitive nature of the files; see Restricted Material.
  - Annual reports, 1984-1993 (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee packets, 1983-1987 (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee/ Board of Directors reorganization, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Board packets, 1988-1995 (12 folders) (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors:
    - Development, 1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Manual, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Membership and correspondence, 1988-1996 (7 folders) (Box 1)
    - New members orientation, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Training manual, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, standing rules, etc., 1989-1994 (Box 2)
  - Executive Director's address, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Executive Director's summary report, 1988 (Box 2)
  - General historical information and pamphlets, 1983-1995, undated (Box 2)
  - Legal issues: Pride Dance, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Long-range planning:
    - Executive Director's goals, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Planning Committee notes, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Marketing session, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Meeting notes, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Strategic planning, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Three-Year Plan, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Mailing lists, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Non-profit status correspondence, 1983-1991 (Box 2)
  - Stationery and logo artwork, undated (Box 2)
  - Staff:
    - Employment policies and procedures, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - Evaluations, 1988-1993 (Box 2)
    - Job announcements, hirings, contracts, and resignations, 1987-1995, undated (Box 2)
    - Job descriptions, undated (Box 2)
    - Memoranda and schedules, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Steering Committee/Board of Directors membership lists, 1986-1995 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1986-1987, undated (also see oversized materials) (Box 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE SERIES
  The Correspondence Series, 1983-1996(bulk 1983-1989), includes requests for information about HIV/AIDS, various lesbian and gay health issues, and the organization itself. The series also includes letters sent by the LGHP in reply to letters received as well as letters sent requesting information and making announcements about new LGHP programming and services.
  The correspondence thoroughly documents the desperate search for any information on AIDS during the early years of the epidemic, as the LGHP received letters from across North Carolina, the entire United States and occasionally from Canada and Mexico requesting information. The LGHP regularly received such letters from elementary and high school students, prisoners, doctors and other health care professionals, and local officials. The correspondence also includes letters and donations made to the LGHP in memory of partners, friends, and family members who died from AIDS; arrangements for and evaluations of LGHP presentations; and requests from other groups and individuals on how to initiate programs and services similiar to those provided by the LGHP.
  Researchers looking for correspondence related to specific projects, to fundraising and grant proposals, to community presentations and events, and with specific organizations should also check the relevant files, where such correspondence may also be housed.
  - 1983-1996 (8 folders) (Box 2)
- CLIPPINGS SERIES
  The Clippings Series, 1983-1996,consists of photocopies of newspaper articles pertaining to LGHP activities and/or members. Most of the clippings originally appeared in the Durham Herald-Sun; the Raleigh News and Observer; The Independent (an alternative newspaper based in Durham); and also in The Front Page, The Newsletter, and Q-Notes ( gay and/or lesbian newspapers based in Raleigh, Durham, and Charlotte, respectively).
  - 1983-1996 (2 folders) (Box 2)
- NEWSLETTERS SERIES
  The Newsletters Series, 1984-1995,chiefly contains the newsletters issued by the LGHP. Also contains scattered materials related to publishing the newsletters.
  - The Newsletter of the Lesbian and Gay Health Project, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
  - Healthlight: The Newsletters of the Lesbian and Gay Health Project and The AIDS Services Project, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- PHOTOGRAPHS SERIES
  The Photographs Series, 1988-1994 and undated relates to various LGHP fundraising events and participation in community events. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Breast Cancer Summit representatives, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Capital Corral collection box, 1988 (Box 2)
  - N.C. Pride, Durham, 1995 (Box 2)
  - The AIDS Services Project: Impact Network safer sex pamphlet, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Triangle Bikes Against AIDS, 1988, 1990 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Triangle Bikes and Hikes, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Triangle Gourmet Gents, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1992-1993, undated (Box 2)
- FINANCIAL PAPERS SERIES
  The Financial Papers Series, 1983-1996,contains monthly, yearly, and other financial statements recording the LGHP's assets and liabilities, independent audit reports, budget statements, ledgers, and papers related to the organization's fundraising efforts through community events and grants.
  The Fundraising subseries includes correspondence, mailing lists, notes, contracts, promotional materials, budgets, and volunteer information pertaining to LGHP fundraising through concerts, bike-a-thons, large community dances and dinners, direct mail solicitations for donations, and participation in local employee donation programs.
  The Grants subseries includes applications, letters of support, correspondence, calls for grant requests, budgets, and final reports and other materials documenting the work of the LGHP, either in search of grant support or in compliance with the terms of received grants. The grant providers represent a wide range of corporations and non-profit foundations and organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Audits, 1990-1991, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Budget:
    - 1994-1995 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Three-Year Forecast, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Financial statements, 1984-1995 (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fundraising:
    - American Dance Festival, 1989-1995 (Box 2)
    - An Evening with Friends, 1995 (Box 2)
    - The Caring Tree, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Charlie Murphy concert, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Heartstrings concert, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - Mailing list solicitation letters, 1990-1996 (Box 3)
    - Major donor campaign materials, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Events, 1986-1991, undated (Box 3)
      - Notes, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
    - North Carolina Community Shares, 1992-1995 (Box 3)
    - Pride Dance, 1987-1992, undated (Box 3)
    - Prom Dance, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Sweet Honey in the Rock concert, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Triangle Bikes Against AIDS, 1987-1991 (5 folders) (also see photographs) (Box 3)
    - Triangle Bikes and Hikes, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Triangle Bikes and Hikes Against AIDS, 1993 (also see photographs) (Box 3)
    - Triangle Miles Against AIDS, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Triangle Bike-a-thons: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
    - Triangle Gourmet Gents, 1990-1991 (also see photographs) (Box 3)
    - Triangle Gourmet Gala, 1992-1995 (also see oversized materials) (Box 3)
    - Workout for Hope event, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Grants:
    - A. J. Fletcher Foundation: HIV diversity conference, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - American Foundation for AIDS Research, 1987-1994 (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - American Foundation for AIDS Research: Black Men United Program, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Avon Breast Health Access Fund, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Broadway Cares, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Bryan Family Foundation, 1990-1993 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Burroughs Wellcome, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    - Centers for Disease Control Conference grant, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Chapel Hill Friends meeting, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Chicago Resource Center, 1983-1992 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Design Industries Foundation for AIDS, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Durham County Home Care Grant, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Greater Triangle Community Foundation, 1991-1992 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - INSURE, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Kate B. Reynolds Health Care Trust, 1991-1992(2 folders ) (Box 4)
    - unspecified (Box 4)
    - Kinko's Community Grant Application, undated (Box 4)
    - Mary Babcock Reynolds Foundation, 1983-1988, 1991 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Ms. Foundation for Women, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Needmor Fund, 1991-1992 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Humanities Council: HIV diversity conference, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Pride, 1995 (Box 4)
    - OUT Fund, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Pride Foundation, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Reducing Our Risks, 1988-1993 (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Robert Woods Johnson Foundation, 1988 (Box 4)
    - United States Conference of Mayors, 1984-1987, 1992 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - United Way, 1990-1992 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Triangle Business and Professional Guild, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation, 1983-1992 (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Ledger, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Lease/Landlord, 1994 (Box 4)
    [Located in box 2]
- PROGRAMMING AND SERVICES SERIES
  The Programming and Services Series, 1983-1995,documents the educational programming and support services the LGHP provided primarily in the Durham-Chapel Hill area.
  Major areas of programming and services documented in this series include:
  Healthline -- The phone line staffed by volunteers serving callers looking for information on health issues or general lesbian/gay/bisexual/transgender community information. This subseries includes volunteer and administrative records, meeting minutes, correspondence, and surveys returned by and evaluations of local health care providers (including hospital staffs, private physicians, psychotherapists, gynecologists, dentists, optometrists, massage therapists, and various other traditional and alternative medicine practitioners).
  Lesbian health -- The bulk of the subseries documents the November 1992 Lesbian Health Conference in Chapel Hill organized by the LGHP, with programs, evaluations, notes, workshop proposals, correspondence, publicity materials, and handouts. The subseries also documents the efforts of the LGHP to establish a Lesbian Health Center and to educate lesbians and bisexual women about their particular risks for HIV and to provide them with safer sex guidelines.
  Presentations -- This subseries includes notes, correspondence, schedules, evaluations, and reports documenting the presentations made by LGHP volunteers and staff to a wide variety of community and social groups, medical schools, civic organizations, and other audiences.
  Reducing Our Risks -- Educational programming funded by the North Carolina state government aimed at reducing the rate of transmission of HIV among gay and bisexual men. This subseries includes the monthly and quarterly reports filed by the LGHP with the state, and the evaluations by state officials of the LGHP's efforts on this project. Also included are correspondence, evaluations, and administrative papers; and materials developed by the LGHP to educate gay and bisexual men about practices more and less likely to transmit HIV, and the programs the organization developed to distribute that information.
  Support groups and workshops -- This subseries includes publicity, notes, and administrative papers related to the support groups and workshops on a broad range of lesbian, gay, and bisexual issues.
  Surveys -- The LGHP conducted several community surveys to assess the current health concerns and needs of local lesbians, gay men, and bisexuals. This subseries documents those projects, including completed questionnaires, notes, and correspondence.
  The AIDS Services Project-- The LGHP organized most of its AIDS-related programming and services under the aegis of The AIDS Services Project (TASP) in 1988,to distinguish that work from its lesbian- and gay-specific projects. The TASP subseries includes materials documenting its buddy program to provide direct emotional and material support to persons living with HIV/AIDS ( PWAs), its Living Positively program that aimed to empower PWAs, its emergency fund for PWAs in dire financial situations, and other HIV/AIDS-related projects. Those materials include correspondence, training manuals and handbooks, publicity materials, volunteer information, notes, reports, and materials distributed to program attendees. Some materials documenting the work of the Buddy program are closed until January 1, 2027 due to the sensitive nature of the information included; see Restricted Materials.
  Volunteers (General) -- This subseries includes correspondence, training materials, volunteer job descriptions, volunteer applications, and other materials documenting the recruitment and supervision of LGHP volunteers. There is some overlap in materials between volunteers with TASP and with other LGHP programs and services. The volunteer applications are open but restricted until January 1, 2097 due to the sensitive nature of the information on the application forms.
  Other information included in the Programming and Services Series includes phone logs, the papers of the Piedmont HIV Health Care Consortium, resource and bibliographic lists, committee notes, and materials documenting smaller programs. The phone logs record the telephone calls received by the LGHP, detailing the everyday work of the organization. The Piedmont HIV Health Care Consortium subseries includes the correspondence and administrative and financial paperwork of this regional case management program funded under the federal Ryan White HIV Care Act. The LGHP acted as the lead agency sponsoring and housing the Consortium for several years.
  - AIDS Education Coordinators, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Coming Out Mentors, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Healthline:
    - Community Resources, 1985-1992, undated (Box 5)
    - Communication Book, 1991-1995 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Correspondence: Volunteers, 1986-1995 (Box 5)
    - Health Care providers:
      - Guidelines, undated (Box 5)
      - Recruitment and training, 1987-1994, undated (Box 5)
      - Referral evaluations, 1985-1991 (Box 5)
      - Referral lists and notes, 1985-1995, undated (Box 5)
      - Services survey, 1984-1994, undated (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Minutes, 1985-1992 (Box 5)
    - Phone counselor exams, 1990s (Box 5)
    - Statistics and logs, 1986-1991, undated (Box 5)
    - Training materials, 1987-1995, undated (Box 5)
    - Volunteer calendars, 1985-1995, undated (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - HIV testing: Miscellaneous, 1985, undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian health:
    - AIDS articles, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Conference, 1992 (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Lesbian Health Center, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Safer sex pamphlet, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Peer counseling, 1990s (Box 5)
  - Phone log, 1991, Mar.-July (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Phone log, 1991, Aug.-1995, Aug. (32 folders) (Box 6)
  - Piedmont HIV Health Care Consortium, 1991-1995 (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Program committee, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Presentations: (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1995 (Box 7)
    - Notes and outlines, 1987-1995, undated (Box 7)
    - Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
    - Reports, 1985-1988 (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - Schedules, 1987-1993, undated (Box 7)
  - Reducing Our Risks:
    - Quarterly report, 1988, Oct.-1993, June (15 folders) (Box 7)
    - Monthly reports, 1989, Sept.-1994, June (12 folders) (Box 7)
    - State report evaluations, 1989-1995 (Box 7)
    - Grant proposals and objectives, 1989-1995 (Box 8)
    - Administrative and financial papers, 1988-1995 (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - AIDS awareness volunteers: Evaluations, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Bar programs, 1988-1991 (Box 8)
    - Black Men United program, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
    - Bookstore programs, 1988-1995 (Box 8)
    - Community Assessment for Program Planning, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Condom and lubricant information, 1990-1995, undated (Box 8)
    - Correspondence:
      - 1988-1995 (Box 8)
      - North Carolina State Government to AIDS service organizations, 1987-1995 (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Each One Teach One program, 1995 (Box 8)
    - HIV testing, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Information cards, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Information packet making, 1990-1995 (Box 8)
    - Pamphlet approval, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
    - Program evaluations (miscellaneous), 1991-1992, undated (Box 8)
    - Safer sex workshops:
      - Administrative papers, 1990 (Box 8)
      - Evaluations, 1990 (Box 8)
      - Fantasies, [ 1990?] (Box 8)
    - Surveys, 1989-1993, undated (Box 8)
    - Training materials, 1990, undated (Box 8)
    - Volunteer and staff information, 1988-1995, undated (Box 8)
    - Women and AIDS, undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-1992 (Box 8)
  - Resources and bibliographies, 1988-1993, undated (Box 8)
  - Support groups and workshops:
    - 1988-1995, undated (Box 8)
    - Joann Loulan, undated (Box 8)
    - Living with HIV, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Surveys:
    - Summary report, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
    - 1991-1993 (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Lesbian health, 1989 (Box 8)
  - The AIDS Services Project:
    - AIDS group reporting forms, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Buddy program:
      - Correspondence, 1987-1995 (Box 8)
      - Manual, undated (3 folders) (Box 8)
      - Monthly report, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Public service announcements, 1988-1991, undated (Box 9)
      - Quarterly report, 1994-1995 (Box 9)
      - Ticket program, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
      - Training Handbook [ 1985?] (Box 9)
      - Training sessions, 1994-1995 (Box 9)
      - Volunteer lists, 1992-1994 (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1985-1990s (Box 9)
    - Client evaluations, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Emergency Fund, 1989-1992, undated (Box 9)
    - Empowerment workshop, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Financial statements, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Impact Network Safer Sex pamphlets: Misc. papers, 1992-1993 (also see photographs) (Box 9)
    - Living Positively:
      - Grants, training manuals, and reports, 1993-1994 (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Durham, 1993-1994, undated (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Henderson and other sites, 1993 (Box 9)
      - State of the State Conference Scholarships, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Pets Are Wonderful Support, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Volunteers (General):
    - Action Day, 1986 (Box 9)
    - Confidentiality statement, 1985-1995 (Box 9)
    - Coordinator's notes, 1986 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1990s (Box 9)
    - Job descriptions, 1990s (Box 9)
    - Volunteer Day, 1986 (Box 9)
- COMMUNITY CONNECTIONS SERIES